上节我们定义了认证加密
In the last segment we defined
authenticated encryption, but I didn't
但我没有真正给大家看，为什么
认证加密是一种合理的安全观点
really show you why authenticated
encryption is the right notion of
本节我想告诉大家，认证加密事实上
security. In this segment I want to show
you that authenticated encryption in fact
是一种很自然的安全观点，我将为大家证实
is a very natural notion of security and
I'll do it by showing you that it defends
认证加密可以抵抗一种叫做选择密文攻击的强大攻击
against a very powerful attack called a
chosen cipher text attack. So in fact we
事实上我们已经看到很多选择密文攻击的例子
already saw a number of examples of a
chosen cipher text attack so imagine the
试想，攻击者有某个他想加密的密文C
adversary has some cipher text C that
it wants to decrypt. And what it can do
例如，攻击者可以欺骗解密服务器去解密某些密文
is, for example, fool the decryption
server into decrypting some cipher text
但这些密文还不是C。我们已经看到一些这样的例子
but not actually the cipher text c. So we
already saw some examples of that. If you
如果大家还记得在本章第一节里，我们看到一个攻击者
remember in the first segment, we looked
at an adversary that can submit arbitrary
可以提交任意密文，如果明文正好以目标端口25开头
cipher text, and if the plaintext happened
to start with destination equals 25, then
那么攻击者可以得到他想要的明文
the adversary is actually given the
plaintext in the clear. So that's an
这例子里攻击者可以获得特定明文的解密结果
example of an adversary that can obtain
the decryption of certain cipher texts but
但不会是全部的密文。我们看的另一个例子是
not all cipher texts. Another example we
saw is an adversary that can learn
攻击者可以通过提交密文给解密者来学到明文
something about the plaintext by
submitting cipher texts to the decrypter.
这个例子里，攻击者提交TCP/IP数据包给解密服务器
So we have this example where the
adversary submits encrypted TCP/IP packets
如果解密服务器发送ACK包
to the decryption server, and if the
decryption server sends back an ACK, the
攻击者就知道了解密后的明文有一个有效的校验和
adversary learns that the decrypted plain
text had a valid checksum. And otherwise,
否则，解密后的明文没有有效的检验和
the decrypted plain text didn't have a
valid check sum. So this is, again, an
这又是一个选择密文攻击的例子，攻击者提交密文
example of a chosen cipher text attack,
where the attacker submits cipher text,
可以学到密文解密的一些信息
and learns something about the decryption
of that cipher text. So to address this
为了解决这种威胁，我们要定义一个非常广义的安全观点
type of threats, we're gonna define a very
general notion of security, called chosen
叫做选择密文安全。这里，我们赋予攻击者强大的力量
cipher text security. So here, we're gonna
give the adversary a lot of power, okay?
他既可以进行选择明文攻击，也可以选择密文攻击
So he can do both chosen plain text
attack, and a chosen cipher text attack.
换句话说，他可以获得他选择的任意信息的加密
In other words, he can obtain the
encryption of arbitrary messages of his
他可以解密他选择的任意密文，而不是挑战密文
choice. And he can decrypt any cipher text
of his choice, other than some challenge
如我给大家之前看的，这是一个很保守的
cipher texts. And as I showed you before,
this is actually a fairly conservative
真实世界的模型。在现实里，攻击者可以经常欺骗解密者
modeling of real life. In real life,
often, the attacker can fool the, the
让解密者去解密特定的密文，但不是所有的密文
decrypter, into decrypting certain cipher
texts for the attacker, but not all cipher
那么这个模型是，攻击者有特定的密文想解密
texts. So the model here is that the
attacker has a certain cipher text that it
它可以与解密者互动
wants to decrypt. It can interact with
the decrypter by issuing these chosen
向解密者发送这些选择密文的询问，解密各种密文
cipher text queries to the decrypter.
Namely, to decrypt various cipher text
除了挑战密文。然后攻击者的目标是
other than the challenge cipher text. And
then the adversary's goal is to break
破坏挑战密文的语义安全。大家注意到
semantic security of the challenge cipher
text. So you notice that we're giving the
我们给了攻击者强大的力量。我们问如何破坏语义安全
adversary a lot of power. And all we're
asking you to do is break semantic
设计出能够对抗这样的攻击者的系统
security. So it's going to be fairly
difficult to design systems that are
是非常困难的。不过我们将会给出答案
secure against such adversaries.
Nevertheless, we're going to do it. So
那么我们来更精确地定义选择密文安全
let's define the chosen cipher text
security model more precisely. So, as
通常，我们有一个密码(E,D)。我们将定义两个实验
usual, we have a cipher (E, D). And we're
gonna define two experiments, experiment
实验0和实验1。大家应该对此很熟悉了
zero and experiment one. So this should
look somewhat familiar by now. The
挑战者开始时选择一个随机密钥
challenger is gonna start off by choosing
a random key. And now the adversary is
现在攻击者提交询问给挑战者。每个询问
可以是两种类型中的一种
gonna submit queries to this challenger.
Every query can be one of two types. It
它可以是选择明文询问，或者是选择密文询问
can be a chosen plain text query, or it
can be a chosen cipher text query. So a
我们知道，一个选择明文询问中
chosen plain text query, as we already
know. Basically, the adversary submits two
攻击者提交两个信息M0和M1，它们的长度相同
messages, M zero and M1. They have to be
the same length. And the adversary
在实验0中，攻击者收到M0的加密结果，或者是
receives the encryption of either M zero
if we're in experiment zero, or M1, if we're
在实验1中，攻击者收到M1的加密结果。
攻击者收到左边或右边的加密结果
in experiment one. So he receives the
encryption of the left or the right
取决于我们是在实验0还是实验1中
depending on whether we were in experiment
zero or in experiment one. The second type
第二种询问更为有趣。其中攻击者提交他选择的任意密文
of query is the more interesting one. This
is where the adversary submits an arbitrary
他获得密文的解密
cipher text of his choice and what he gets
back is the decryption of that cipher
大家注意攻击者可以获得他选择的任意密文的解密结果
text. So you notice the adverary's allowed
to decrypt arbitrary cipher texts of his
(此处decrypt有歧义，注意攻击者不能自己解密)
唯一的限制是，他的密文不是选择明文攻击的询问中
choice. The only restriction is that the
cipher text is not one of the cipher texts
他所获得的密文之一。当然这不合理
that were obtained as a result of a CPA
query. And of course this wouldn't be fair
因为攻击者可以通过CPA询问，轻松获得密文
otherwise, because the attacker can simply
take one cipher text that was obtained
得到的是M0或M1的加密结果
from a CPA query. That's gonna to be
either the encryption of M0 or the
如果攻击者可以提交特定密文的CCA询问
encryption of M1. If he could submit a CCA
query for that particular cipher text, he
他会获得M0或M1作为答复，这样攻击者就会知道
will in response either obtain M0 or M1,
and then he'll know whether he is in experiment
他是在实验0还是实验1了。这不合理。所以我们说
zero or experiment one. So this wouldn't
be fair. So we say that the CPA cipher
攻击者收到的CPA密文都是挑战密文
texts that he received are the challenge
cipher texts. And he's allowed to decrypt
攻击者允许获得任何他选择的密文的解密结果，
这些挑战密文除外
any cipher texts of his choice, other than
these challenge cipher texts. And as
通常，攻击者的目标是确定他是在实验0，还是实验1
usual, his goal is to determine whether
he's in experiment zero, or in experiment
我要强调，这是一个极为强大的攻击者
one. So I'm gonna emphasize again, that
this is an extremely powerful adversary.
他可以获得除了挑战密文外，任意密文的解密结果
One that can decrypt any cipher text of
his choice, other than the challenge
但他依然不能区分他是在实验0或实验1中
cipher text. And still, he can't
distinguish whether he is in experiment
通常，我们说密码是CCA安全的
zero, or in experiment one. So, as usual,
we say that the cipher is CCA secure,
选择密文安全的，如果攻击者在实验0和实验1中
chosen cipher text secure, if the
adversary behaves the same in experiment
表现一致。他无法区分这两个实验
zero as it does in experiment one. Namely, it
cannot distinguish the two experiments. So
那么我们从一个简单例子开始，来证明事实上
let's start with a simple example, and
show that, in fact, CBC with a random IV,
带随机IV的CBC不是CCA安全的，不是选择密文安全的
is not CCA secure, is not secure against
chosen cipher text attacks. So let's see
我们看这是为什么。攻击者在一开始
why that's the case. So what the
adversary's gonna start by doing, he's
他提交两个不同的明文M0和M1
gonna simply submit two distinct messages,
M0 and M1. And let's just pretend that
我们假定这两个信息都是单个分组的，然后攻击者
these messages are one block messages. And
what he's gonna get back is the CBC
会获得M0或M1的加密结果。大家注意密文只有一个分组
encryption of either M0 or
M1. You notice the cipher text only has
因为明文只有一个分组长
one block, because the plain texts were
only one block long. Now what is the
攻击者要怎么做？他要修改这个得到的密文C
attacker gonna do? Well, he's gonna modify
this cipher text C that he was given into
变成C'，仅仅是改变了IV。他将IV异或1
C prime simply by changing the IV. Okay?
So he just takes the IV and XORs it with
完事了。给一个新的不同于C的密文C'
one. That's it. This gives a new cipher
text, C prime, which is different from C
因此攻击者完全可以提交C'，作为他的
and as a result it's perfectly valid for
the adversary to submit C prime as its
选择密文攻击的询问。他让挑战者为他解密C'
chosen cipher text query. So he
asks the challenger please decrypt this C
由于C'不等于C，挑战者必须解密C'
prime for me. The challenger, because c
prime is not equal to c, must decrypt c
现在我们看到，解密C'会发生什么？
prime. And now let's see, what happens
when he decrypts C prime? Well, what's the
C'的解密是什么？大家记得第一节里
decryption of c prime, let me ask you. So
you probably remember from the first
如果我们把IV异或1，明文也会异或1
segment that if we xor the IV by one, that
simply xors the plaintext by one. So now
现在，攻击者收到了M0异或1，或是M1异或1
that adversary received M0 xor one, or M1
xor one, and now he can perfectly tell
攻击者就完全可以确定他在实验0，还是在实验1
whether he's in experiment zero and, or in
experiment one. So the advantage of this
攻击者的优势是1，因为他可以轻松确定他在哪个实验
adversary is basically one, because he can
very easily tell which experiment he's in.
因此它可以赢得这个选择密文安全的游戏
And as a result he can win the chosen
cipher text security game. So if you think
大家想一想，会看出这个攻击游戏抓住了
about it for a second, you'll see that
this attack game exactly captured the first
我们看过的第一个主动攻击，攻击者稍微改变一点他得到的密文
active attack that we saw, where the
adversary slightly changed the cipher text
然后他让解密者为他解密
that he was given. And then he got the
decrypter to decrypt it for him. And
因此，攻击者可以窃听本不该给他的信息
therefore, he was able to eavesdrop on
messages that were not intended for the
那么我想再次强调，这个选择密文攻击
adversary. So I wanna emphasize again that
this chosen cipher text game really does
在现实中确实会发生，攻击者可以提交密文给解密者
come up in real life, where the adversary
can submit cipher texts to the decrypter
解密者可以透露明文的信息
and the decrypter can reveal information
about the plain text, or it can give the
或者干脆给攻击者特定密文对应的明文，
但其他密文不能给明文
plain text outright to the adversary for
certain cipher texts but not others. So
这是一个非常自然的安全观点。问题是
this is a very natural notion of security,
and the question is, how do we design
我们如何设计CCA安全的加密系统？我说，
我们之前定义的这个认证加密的观点
crypto-systems that are CCA secure? So I
claim that this authenticated encryption
已经蕴涵了选择密文安全
notion that we defined before actually
implies chosen cipher text security, and
这也是为什么认证加密的观点如此自然
this is why authenticated encryption is
such a natural concept. Okay? So the
这个定理说，如果密码能提供认证加密
theorem basically says, well, if you give
me a cipher that provides authenticated
这个密码就可以抵抗选择密文攻击
encryption, the cipher can withstand
chosen cipher text attacks. And more
更精确地，这个定理说了如下事实。
如果我们有一个攻击者，提交了q个询问
precisely, the theorem says the following.
If we have an adversary that issues Q
换句话说，最多q个CPA询问和q个CCA询问
queries, in other words, at most, q CPA
queries and q chosen cipher text queries,
那么有两个有效的攻击者B1和B2，满足这个不等式
then there are two efficient adversaries,
B1 and B2, that satisfy this inequality
由于这个机制有认证加密，我们知道
here. So since the scheme has
authenticated encryption, we know that
这个量是可忽略的，因为它是CPA安全的
this quantity is negligible because it's
CPA secure. And we know that this
这个量是可忽略的，因为加密机制有密文完整性
quantity is negligible because the
encryption scheme has cipher text
因此，由于两项都是可忽略的
integrity. And as a result, since both
terms are negligible we know that
攻击者赢得CCA游戏的优势也是可忽略的
adversary's advantage in winning the CCA
game is also negligible. So let's prove
我们来证明这个定理。这个定理容易证明
this theorem. It's actually a very simple
theorem to prove. And so let's just do it
我们用图像来证明它。这里我们有两份CCA游戏
as proof by pictures. Okay, so here we
have two copies of the CCA game, so this
这个是实验0，下面这个是实验1
would be experiment zero. And the bottom
one is experiment one. You can see the
大家可以看到，攻击者提交CPA询问和CCA询问
adversary's issuing CPA queries, and he's
issuing CCA queries, and at the end he
最后他输出一个特定的猜测b，记为b'
outputs, you know, a certain guess b,
let's call it b prime, and our goal is to
我们的目标是证明这个b'在两种情况下都是不可区分的
show that this b prime is
indistinguishable in both cases. In other
换句话说，上面这个游戏中b'=1的概率
words, probability that b prime is equal
to one in the top game is the same as the
与下面这个游戏中b'=1的概率是一样的
probability that b prime is equal to one
in the bottom game. Okay, so the way we're
我们如下证明之。首先，我们稍微改变一下挑战者
gonna do it is the following. Well, first
of all, we're gonna change the challenger
不再输出CCA询问的解密
a little bit, so that instead of actually
outputting the decryption of CCA queries,
攻击者会输出符号⊥
the challenger is just gonna always output
bottom. So every time the adversary
每次攻击者提交一个CCA询问，挑战者都说符号⊥
submits a CCA query, the challenger says
bottom. And I claim that these two
我说这两个游戏事实上是不可区分的。换句话说
games are, in fact, indistinguishable. In
other words, the adversary can't
攻击者不能区分这两个游戏，原因很简单
distinguish these two games, for the
simple reason that, because the scheme has
因为机制有密文完整性，攻击者不能产生一个密文
cipher text integrity, the adversary
simply cannot create a cipher text that's
不是从C1到C_i-1中的，可以解密到不是符号⊥的其他东西
not in C1 to C_i-1 that decrypts to
anything other than bottom. That is the
这时密文完整性的定义。因此，因为密文完整性
definition of cipher text integrity. And
as a result, again, because of cipher text
一定有每个攻击者提交的选择密文的询问
integrity, it must be the case that every
chosen cipher text query that the
得到的都是符号⊥。如果事实上攻击者可以区分
adversary issues results in bottom. If the
adversary, in fact, could distinguish
左边的游戏和右边的游戏，这意味着
between the left game and the right game,
that would mean that at some point he
他可以设法提交一个CCA询问，可以解密到不是符号⊥的
某些东西，这样我们就可以使用这个攻击者
issued a query that decrypted to something
other than bottom. And that we could use
来破坏机制的密文完整性
to then break cipher text integrity of the
scheme. And since the scheme has
由于这个机制有密文完整性，左右两个游戏不可区分
cipher-text integrity, these left and
right games are indistinguishable. Okay,
这一犀利的论断展示了，当有密文完整性时
so that's kind of acute argument that
shows that it's very easy to respond to
很容易回复选择密文的询问
chosen cipher-text queries when you have
cipher-text integrity. And the same thing
同样的事情应用在下面这个游戏上，
我们可以让选择密文攻击的回复
exactly applies on the bottom, where we
can simply replace the chosen cipher-text
总是符号⊥。很好，现在
responses by just always saying bottom.
Okay, very good. But now, since the chosen
因为选择密文的询问总是以同样的方式回复
cipher text queries always respond in the
same way, they're not giving the adversary
不会给攻击者任何的信息。攻击者总是知道
any information. The adversary always
knows that we're always gonna just respond
我们会以符号⊥回复，所以我们可以去除这些询问了
with bottom. So we might as well just
remove these queries, 'cause they don't
因为它们不对攻击者提供任何信息
contribute any information to the
adversary. But now, once we remove these
一旦我们去除了这些询问，剩下的游戏看上去应该很熟悉了
queries, the resulting game should look
fairly familiar. The top right game, and
右上和右下的游戏是由CPA安全的定义得来的
the bottom right game are basically the two
games that come up in the definition of
由于这个机制是CPA安全的，我们知道
CPA security. And as a result, because the
scheme is CPA secure, we know that the
攻击者不能区分上下两个游戏
adversary can't distinguish the top from
the bottom. And so now, by this change of
通过这段演绎，我们证明了所有这些游戏都是等价的
reasoning, we've proven that all of these
games are equivalent. And in particular,
特别地，最初的两个游戏也是等价的
the original two games that we started
with are also equivalent, and therefore,
因此，攻击者不能区分左上和左下
the adversary can't distinguish the top
left from the bottom left. And therefore,
因此这个机制是CCA安全的。这给大家一些直观感受
the scheme is CCA secure. So this gives
you the intuition as to why authenticated
为什么认证加密这个概念如此好，因为它蕴涵了
encryption is such a cool concept. Because
primarily it implies security against
对抗选择密文攻击的安全性。我们说过
chosen cipher text attacks. Okay, so as we
said authenticated encryption
验证加密确保了私密性。即使攻击者可以解密
ensures confidentiality. Even if the
adversary can decrypt a subset of the
一个密文子集，更一般地，即使攻击者可以实施
一个广义的选择密文攻击
cipher text, and more generally, even if
he can mount a general chosen cipher text attack,
他依然不能破坏系统的语义安全
he still is not going to be able to break
semantic security of the system. However,
但有两个重要的局限性要记住：首先
it is important to remember the two
limitations. First of all, it does not
它不能阻止重放攻击。我们必须做些什么
prevent replay attacks on its own. We're
going to have to do something in addition
以抵抗重放攻击。我们将看到几个例子
to defend against replay attacks. We're
going to see several examples where if the
如果解密者透露了更多关于为什么密文被拒绝的信息
decryption engine reveals more information
about why a cipher text is rejected, it
解密者不仅仅输出符号⊥，它还输出更多信息
doesn't just output bottom, but it
actually outputs more information, say, by
比如说，计时攻击。这就解释了为什么密文被拒绝了
timing attacks. And that explains why the
cipher text is rejected. Then in fact that
然后事实上，这可以完全摧毁认证加密系统的安全性
can completely destroy security of the
authenticated encryption system. So we'll
下节我们将看到这样一些可爱的攻击
see some cute attacks like this in a later
segment. Okay. So, in the next segment
下节我们将组建认证加密系统
we're gonna turn to constructing
authenticated encryption systems.